Guide to the David Garrick Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
David Garrick collection
1733-1778
GEN MSS 282
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
Contains letters from Garrick to: James Stonhouse (regarding his first meeting with Hannah More), Edward Thompson, and Benjamin Victor; manuscripts of poems and epitaphs by Garrick; and a few manuscripts of poems by other people.
Garrick, David, 1717-1779
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to David Garrick, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection.
Epitaphs; Poetry; Cymon; Garrick, David, 1717-1779; More, Hannah, 1745-1833; Stonhouse, James, Sir, 1716-1795; Thompson, Edward, 1738?-1786; Victor, Benjamin, -1778
- Letters from David Garrick, n.d.; Series I
  - ALS to [Domenico] Angelo, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Purchase, 1959.
  - ALS to [Dorothy Savile Boyle], the Countess of Burlington, London, [1749] Sep 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Endorsed: "Mr. G. recd Oct. 1st."
    Purchase, 1955.
  - Manuscript copy of letter to James Clutterbuck, Bath, 1776 Jan 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift, 1958.
  - ALS to George Colman, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Purchase, 1965.
  - ALS to George Colman, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Accompanied by engraving of Garrick.
    Purchase, 1970.
  - Draft of letter to James Lacy, 1745 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    With corrections and notes in an
    unidentified hand.
    Accompanied by a copy of the portrait
    of Garrick by R. E. Pine in the
    National Portrait Gallery.
    Gift, 1940.
  - LS to the countess of Rochfort, [1766?] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Draft in an unknown hand; endorsed by
    Garrick.
    Purchase, 1983.
  - ALS to Sir James Stonhouse, Hampton, 1774 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Account of his first meeting with
    Hannah More and detailed advice to
    her regarding dramatic composition.
    Purchase, 1956.
  - ALS to Edward Thompson, Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - ALS to Benjamin Victor, Hampton, Aug 18 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    With Garrick's seal in red wax.
    From the collection of Dr. Max
    Thorek, with his stamp.
    Gift, 1960.
  - ALS to "my dear Dr.", May 17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Purchase, 1957.
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Dated "Monday night 10th."
    Endorsed in an unidentified hand:
    "Mr. Garrick to my father."
    Purchase, 1961.
- Writings of David Garrick, n.d.; Series II
  - "A Mademoiselle Fanni, Antoinette, Marie, Samarette de Raucour...", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    On verso is "Reponse de Mons.
    Villette." Two poems, holograph.
    Copied but probably not composed by
    Garrick. In French.
  - "The Charrader's Recantation to Sir William Hamilton", [1772?] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Autograph manuscript poem of 5
    stanzas, signed D. G.
    Gift, 1937.
  - "Cymon", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Autograph manuscript fragment of a
    play based on Dryden's "Cymon and
    Iphigenia."
    Gift, 1959.
  - Epigram written on the publication of Doctor Johnson's Dictionary, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Gift, 1979.
  - "Epilogue", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Autograph manuscript poem of 8 lines.
    First line: "Should ever discord or
    disorder reign."
  - "Epilogue for L--- S--- After Playing the Character of Calista", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Autograph manuscript with additions
    and corrections in the hand of the
    author.
    Purchase, 1975.
  - "Epilogue for the Choleric Man", [1774] (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Manuscript poem of 54 lines in an
    unidentified hand. Endorsed by
    Garrick: "Epil: for Choleric Man."
  - "Epilogue for the Fund", 1776 May (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Manuscript poem in an unidentified
    hand. Endorsed by Garrick: "Epilogue
    for the Fund with the last
    alterations. May 1776."
  - Epitaph for Bernard Hale, [1773] (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Autograph manuscript poem of 12 lines
    signed "D. G."
  - "Epitaph for the Lord Spencer's Lopper, Topper, & Sweeper of Gardens", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Autograph manuscript poem of 8 lines
    signed "D. G." An epitaph for Thomas
    Longford, Lord Spencer's servant.
  - "Epitaph for the Revd. Mr. Allot", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Poem, holograph.
  - Epitaph on Spranger Barry, [1777] (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Manuscript poem of 10 lines in an
  - [The first thing is that thing without which I hold...], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Autograph manuscript riddle of 8
    lines. A copy of this riddle
    (attributed to George Selwyn) was
    sent by Horace Walpole to William
    Mason in a letter of 1773 Jul 29. A
    possible answer to the riddle is
    "ribband box."
  - "Garrick to His Infidel Physician", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Autograph manuscript poem, signed
    with initials.
  - [His fame throughout the world...], [1777] (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Holograph, four lines of verse, on
    Sir Joshua Reynolds, from third
    stanza of poem in The Public Advertiser, 1777 Apr 29. With
    clipping of entire poem and of
    poem from preceding day to which this
    is a reply.
  - "An Invitation to Ld. Chatham Passing into Devonshire from Mr. Garrick", 1771 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Manuscript poem of 8 lines in an
  - "More Road Verses to the D: of Devonshire, Upon Her Leaving Her Muff & Sending Some Charming Lines to D: G:", [1778] (Box 1, Folder 29)
    unidentified hand. On verso is
    Garrick's "Road Verses Continued."
  - "Ode to Musick for the Catch-Club", 1778 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Autograph manuscript.
  - "Oh! For a Muse of Fire &c. to Tell", [1769] (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Three alternative stanzas for "An Ode
    Upon Dedicating a Building and
    Erecting a Statue to Shakespeare, at
    Stratford-upon-Avon". Not in
    Garrick's hand.
    Purchase, 1942.
  - "The Pleasures of May at Batheaston", [1775] (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Manuscript poem of 24 lines written
    in an unidentified hand. Endorsed by
    Garrick: "May for the Urn at
    Batheaston."
  - Prologue for the benefit of the theatrical fund of the Drury Lane Theatre, [1766] (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Manuscript fragment of 14 lines in an
  - "Remarks (and Pretty Obvious Ones) on the 41st Letter" (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Autograph manuscript, with bookplate
    of Garrick. Removed from: A Journal of Eight Days Journey from Portsmouth to Kingston Upon Thames by Jonas
    Hanway (London, 1756).
  - "Road Verses to a Certain Bird, Who Endeavored to Pass Upon the Blackbird for a Sparrow", [1778] (Box 1, Folder 35)
    unidentified hand. On verso is a poem
    by Georgiana Cavendish, Duchess of
    Devonshire, beginning "The blackbird
    whose melodious throat..."
  - ['Tis true, as some say, that to death from our birth...], [1771] (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Four lines of autograph manuscript
    verse.
    Purchase, 1954.
  - "To a Young Counsellor of the Inner Temple", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Autograph manuscript poem of 8 lines,
    signed "D. G." On verso: "Upon
    Thompson's Defection to Mr.
    Crawford."
  - "To My Friend ____ Upon His Great Credulity" (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Manuscript poem of 13 lines in an
  - "The Unsuspecting Irish Gentleman", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Autograph manuscript poem.
  - "Upon D. G.'s Reception at Wynnstay", 1777 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Autograph manuscript poem of 20 lines
    Tinker 1052A
  - "Upon Lord Spencer's Illness", [1764] (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Autograph manuscript poem regarding
    John Spencer, Lord Althorp.
  - "Upon Mr. G...Being Ask'd Why He Did Not Write Something Upon the Duchess of Devonshire's Illness", 1778 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Manuscript poem of 12 lines in an
    Garrick: "1778 Lines upon the Duchess
    of Devonshire's Illness 78."
  - "Upon Mr. Sh[irle]y's Subscribing Himself Crabstick", [1758] (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Manuscript poem, in the hand of an
    amanuensis, regarding William
    Shirley. On verso: [Advice to
    Crabstick].
  - "Upon the Subscription to the New Rooms at Bath...by Mrs. F--Y", 1769 Apr 20 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Autograph manuscript poem of 6 lines.
    Written on an album leaf, signed
    "F--y." On verso is Garrick's "Upon
    Plomer's Being Pull'd by ye Nose by
    Mr. Orme."
  - "Upon the Two Justices - Foolding and Addlebraine" (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - "Upon ye Egyptian Hall at York, Built by Lord Burlington & Much Neglected by ye People of ye Town", 1753 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Purchase, 1963.
  - "Verses Written in a Prayer Book Given to Me by Lady Burlington", 1753 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Autograph manuscript poem of 4 lines
    regarding Dorothy Savile Boyle,
    Countess of Burlington.
- Writings of Others, [1776] Jun 2; Series III
  - Courtenay, John. Complimentary verse addressed to Garrick at the time of his retirement from the stage, London, [1776] Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Filce, Joseph. Bond for 400 pounds to Garrick, [Hampton], 1767 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Purchase, 1946.
  - Lovibond, Edward. Manuscript of "Ode to Captivity Written During the Last War" (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Endorsed by Garrick on the verso of
    p. 3.
  - Morell, Thomas. "A Modern Conversation," [London], 1733 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Autograph manuscript addressed to
    D. G. and signed T. M.
- Other, n.d.; Series IV
  - Complimentary verses addressed to Garrick and miscellaneous verses sent to him (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "David Garrick. Celebrated Actor, 1716-1779", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Manuscript biographical sketch.
  - Manuscript (facsimile) order of admittance, [London], [1779?] (Box 1, Folder 54)
    With facsimile note by Mrs. Garrick
    describing the order. Accompanied by
    engraving of Garrick.
    Gift, 1954.